[Music]
we're fast approaching the age of the
superhuman and we're doing this by
transcending the bounds of evolution
so buckle up and prepare to enter the
world of the iron man executive
with dr daniel strickland we'll explore
the limitless human potential through
cutting-edge science
new technologies and medical advancement
here is your host
dr daniel stickler
welcome back to this edition of the iron
man executive i'm dr
dan and as usual we have another really
exciting
and educational show coming up for you i
do want to
reiterate a lot of the stuff that we've
been talking about about all the
exciting things that have been happening
at the appearance center for human
potential where we have
recently launched the appearon academy
that's
a p e i r o n dot academy
not a dot com but dot academy you can go
there
check out all the new courses that we're
teaching now in
epigenetics we're actually having a
certification in epigenetic coaching
this is about 120 hours of training
and most of that is done by me
i also have some really amazing coaches
that are going to be
teaching this with me coaches that are
tops in their field in the realm of
coaching tops in their field in the
realm of
business development for health coaches
health and wellness
so if you are an existing health and
wellness coach a physician
a chiropractor a nutritional therapist
a dietitian or somebody who just wants
to get into health coaching because you
have a huge passion for it
go on and check this out because this
will take you to a whole new level
epigenetic coaching is the new paradigm
of medicine
and after you hear the intro on that
website you
will be convinced plus we have a lot of
fun in creating this tribe so
be sure to check it out now you heard me
talk last week about
a essentially an affiliate partnership
that we have developed with
neurohacker collective this is a company
that
manufactures the the neurohacker qualia
brain supplementation and i tell you the
stuff is really
out of this world i mean it it truly
does exactly
what you expect it to do and it really
is just taking the brain to a whole new
level
of optimization we found this
after i had referred several patients to
it to try it out because it really had a
mix
of nutrients that i said you know this
is really the real deal
and so it led down the road to several
conversations
with the company and eventually um i had
some conversations with
daniel schmokenberger who is one of the
founders
and the guy is absolutely fascinating so
i asked him to come on the podcast
and to talk about the whole neurohacker
collective and a little bit about the
qualia product
and he agreed to do so this is an
interview that is really out of this
world
i mean daniel i i don't even venture to
give a good intro to daniel because
any anything i try to do as far as a bio
will really
not do justice to who daniel
schmoktenberger is
so what i did is i asked him to kind of
tell us about himself
and about the company and their mission
in the intro to this interview
and i can tell you he is someone who
takes an entire systems approach to
absolutely everything you know in our
medical practice we use a systems
approach
to health and wellness and it's this
whole interaction of all these systems
involved well he takes that to a whole
new level of not only health and
wellness but to
business to commerce to life
in general and you're going to be blown
away by this interview so
sit back and have a listen
all right so i've got a great guest with
us today his name is
daniel schmochtenberger and he has
agreed to come on and talk to us
about various topics but most
importantly we want to focus
on the company that is part of his
vision
and some of the products that they have
but let's start off uh
daniel talking about who you are just
give us some background and a little bit
about what makes you you
hmm very open question
so i think a meaningful place to start
is i was
fortunate to be home educated as a kid
in a way that was kind of a an
educational experiment that my parents
wanted to run
which was uh what happens if you give a
kid no
curriculum at all expose them to
everything you can see what they're
interested in and facilitate the
interests
so i didn't have a fixed amount of
social studies and english and etc
and what was really interesting about
that of course it means that there are
certain things that are part of normal
general education that i wasn't
interested in and just didn't get so
my my handwriting is illegible my
spelling is
bad but uh but i go very deeply into all
the sciences early on
and i didn't even think of them as
separate divisions because
the division between biology and
chemistry and physics are
useful for us for trying to create
curriculum
but obviously universe is radically
integrated and you have
causal arrows pointing in uh up and down
directions
and so studying it that way it was just
the study of how
universe works and so all the areas of
science
all of the philosophic disciplines that
created context for maybe why is science
that way why is the nature of reality
the way that it is
and then all the different areas of
activism how can we
understand the nature of reality better
so we can participate in
alleviating suffering making a higher
quality of life experience possible for
everyone
so that braid of activism science and
philosophy
is kind of core to who i am and
all of the various endeavors fit within
it yeah and that's why i wanted to bring
that up because
looking at your background i mean you
have a very diverse
kind of entrepreneurial background and
activism background can you tell us
about some of the projects that
they came from that yeah so working in
activism early on
this was everything from ecological work
to uh
civil rights work to animal rights work
and
one of the things that i saw also having
a background in interdisciplinary
science
ended up leading fortunately to a
background in system science
understanding how
seemingly different things actually fit
together into self-organizing holes into
whole systems
and so taking a system science approach
to
activism i saw okay here's an area where
we're trying to
say protect an animal from poaching and
the answer is
say it was an elephant we're gonna put
bigger fences around the preserves and
create harsher sentencing for poachers
but we're not addressing the underlying
poverty of the people that can't meet
their needs
any other way adequately other than
poaching we're not addressing the
value system and why it's conditioned
that way towards
animals not addressing macroeconomics
that leads to poverty we're not
addressed like there's so many things
that aren't being addressed
that if we succeed at getting the fences
up then the poachers move to some other
animal somewhere else or
you know some other problem and so
starting to look at
what would it take to actually
meaningfully address all of the things
that need addressed from a system's
point of view what would a whole
system's design upgrade for humanity
look like so
relatively early on that became my
primary inquiry and so this was
maybe we actually can't change the
future of
education to be optimal education that
brings forth the uh
the full potential and capability of
humans if we don't change macroeconomics
to where we're not having to prepare
those kids for a workforce in the way
that we are now but we're preparing them
for
a different macroeconomic structure
where the facilitation of their unique
genius capabilities is you know is
supported in terms of
the system they're coming into et cetera
right so start looking at what is the
future of
macroeconomics what's the future of
governance what's the future of
education of healthcare that are optimum
factoring the interconnectivity of
all of those things upgrading so this
was the beginning of
starting a think tank that then worked
with a number of other
leading edge think tanks on the topic of
fundamental restructure of civilization
in ways that could prevent current
problems
that really must be prevented
catastrophic and existential risks that
otherwise have too high of a probability
currently
that could address the underlying causes
of so much of the
unnecessary human induced suffering and
that could produce highest quality of
life
for the highest potential quality of
life for all life
and so then it's just really been a
refinement
of this process of what really needs to
happen
and how do we go about doing that and
for a while i worked with
large ngos and companies and trying to
implement some of the ideas through
there
through those vehicles until realizing
that those vehicles
really couldn't do the things that were
necessary
the groups that were working on hunger
were quite happy
to address starvation in areas of
extreme poverty
by bringing industrial agriculture to
the area to be able to create more food
production there
even if that meant more nitrogen runoff
leading to
faster dead zones in the ocean because
those weren't the metrics they were
tasked with
and it doesn't mean they were really
happy it just means that the nature of
here's the metrics you're tasked with
and they are they are inter
connected with other things but that's
not they're the focus of how that
interconnectivity is addressed
is just outside of the macro systems
that uh you know those structures are
part of and so eventually
said all right well let's just actually
look at how to build things from scratch
that can obsolete
the things that need obsoleted well
that's uh you know there's a reason
behind why i wanted you to go into that
story i i've
we've talked previously and and i know
the story and i've read some background
on it
but it's also one of the approaches we
use in
our new paradigm of medicine of human
potential medicine where we look at this
entire biospherical approach so we look
at the interactions of
all aspects of the human being including
environmental interactions and sleep
stress
thoughts brain function all of that so
you've taken this into just this amazing
think take process and here's here's
what i'm leading to
is the the creation of neurohacker
collective
that neurohacker collective actually
came from this this
think tank and i think that's just
fascinating the way that
the the organization i think a lot of
people will look at neurohacker
and they'll see the quality of product
and they'll think oh they're a
supplement company but
that's far from even close to what
neurohacker collective is
two things one is you said the approach
that we're describing for
civilization design and the approach
that you advocate for medicine
are very related they are very related
because the human
body and the human mind body environment
system
is a complex system and so if you try
and do
you know reductionist parts based
approach
it just it works for acute things it
doesn't work for complex things
and so all right there is too much ldl
so we're going to give a statin but we
didn't really ask why there's too much
ldl
and what the externalities side effects
of the statin are going to be and you
know that approach just doesn't work for
complex illness and it doesn't work for
comprehensive wellness optimization so
you have to say
across all of the different body systems
are there ways that the gut affects
the brain yes through the entire nervous
system through
uh the microbiota through you know so
the division between neurology and
gastroenterology
we just can't you can't maintain
specialism across those boundaries you
can't maintain specialism across
the genetic bottom-up organization and
the connectomic
top-down organization because they're
influencing each other in real time
and so you look at the body as a whole
complex adaptive system regulatory
system and then you say
our goal is to increase the resilience
of the entire system the homeostatic
capacity of the whole system
how do we go about doing that and to see
disease as
where some deviations from homeostasis
exceeded
the homeostatic capacity of the system
leading to pathophysiology and how do we
then bring that back and you know
restore system resilience
when we're looking at an ecosystem or
we're looking at
human civilization systems they're also
complex adaptive systems where
the goal similarly the economics and the
environment are inter-affecting each
other
inexorably right the all the social
systems
governance law or inter-affecting
infrastructure
and so you have to say well again
what would a really resilient system
look like and
it's not going to look like exponential
growth of a materials economy on a
finite planet there's just no way
that could ever be resilient right it's
not going to look like for-profit
a military-industrial complex while
trying to create peace or for-profit
sick care while trying to create health
was not going to look like places where
the incentives are misaligned with the
goals
and so you say well what would a really
resilient system look like
and so very like why humanitarian aid
why all of our approaches to peace and
security and global problem solving
haven't been working
is the exact same reason allopathic
medicine doesn't work for complex issues
is
i mean we very much have an allopathic
system of governance
that is dealing with symptoms rather
than causes dealing with things as
separate issues that really are
interconnected issues so
you know we apply the same systems for
looking at medicine in the body
because they are complex systems
optimization
now why we started focusing on bringing
forward
solutions for future of well-being
science which would include what we've
called medicine in the past
how to move from disease states to
wellness states but
also how to maintain and optimize and
continuously evolve states of higher and
higher
well-being higher and higher system
resilience and we're
starting not in the medicine space but
in the optimization space with neural
hypercollective and specifically in the
mind brain space how do we optimize the
mind brain
interface for optimally sovereign humans
humans whose agency whose intelligence
whose sentience are all
you know evolving and interconnectedly
evolving
the reason why that is one of the
critical things that has to happen
for all of the meaningful shifts that
have to happen on the planet-wide level
is that
when we look at all of the problems that
we want to change whether we're talking
about violence
you know at a crime level or violence at
a war level
or violence against nature at a
biodiversity loss level
or like all of those issues that we're
trying to address
are caused by human behavior and
all of the solutions we want to bring
about have to come from human behavior
so then the question becomes
what are all the things that influence
human behavior and that can influence it
in destructive or constructive
directions
and obviously economics influences human
behavior if if you create an economic
system
where war is profitable or an economic
system where a whale
is worth a million dollars dead on
a fishing boat but is worth nothing
alive that economic system predisposes
destructive behavior so you need to
change economics to incentivize
for any agent that which is also
positive for all other agents in the
commons that is a radically
different system of macroeconomics so
economics and social systems as a whole
influence behavior
environment influences behavior our
psychology
and our definition of success and
self-influence behavior so does our
physiology
and everyone who has ever felt
shitty when they were sick or had a
hangover
or hormones or neurotransmitters were
out of balance or just had a headache
knows that
there are certain states of
consciousness that are just unaccessible
when your physiology is off and other
ones that are almost unavoidable
that affect your experience and your
behavior and the same is true when your
system
is more in tune and so realizing that
empathy runs on certain neural networks
in the brain that consciousness is
running on the hardware of physiology
and if the hardware physiology is
damaged or
just down regulated or out of tune that
there are whole aspects of
of experience and behavior that are just
either down regulated or not possible
in the question of how do we optimize
physiology
for optimal human experience and
behavior right people who
have complex problem solving have high
emotional resilience have high
you know agency etc so that they have
the predispositions and capability
to really be assets to
the balance sheet of nature rather than
liability yeah and
you know the this whole complex
interactive
aspect i mean you you focused in on
allopathic medicine but i see it in
functional medicine as well
i mean i think the the whole system has
come down to
treating the human being as a diseased
state there isn't this
this option for optimization in the
medical communities right now
and you know that's our driving force is
to create that
that option for people who say you know
what we're not really broken and
how can we how can we optimize this
system to take us to a new level
of existence a new level of functioning
not in a hedonistic way but in a in a
kind of eu demonic way to bring the the
whole
population into this into this new realm
um
josh metaldorf a friend of mine who i
interviewed on the on
this show is he wrote the book cracking
the aging code and he compared
the current medical paradigm to you know
hearing the call of a man overboard and
you run and you see a guy
thrashing in the water and you're
throwing life preservers to him and he's
not reaching for them
and you can keep throwing them but he's
never going to reach for them because
it's a
it's a system that's that's broken that
you can't fix
no matter how hard you try so i think
you know there is a role for that
disease model aspect but
you know we're with the advances we have
i mean this is something that we need
this new approach to
and you know you've you've ventured into
this
realm with the neurohacker collective
the the
qualia product that you have created
with that is just
an amazing product to optimize
uh human function yeah so we talk about
the future of
well-being science more than we talk
about the future of medicine because
medicine
is the system of uh how do we deal
with illness and of course once illness
is there
our well-being science system already
failed
our goal is to maintain and optimize and
evolve well-being
and then of course there there will be
times where something happens right
there's some deviation from homeostasis
that's beyond the system's capacity and
so we come in to help
bring you know help resolve it but the
goal is recognizing that it's actually
the system's own self-organization that
is what makes the person better it's
just now what things do we
help supply the system with so it can do
that so coming to uh
jumping forward and if if it's
interesting to get into how we define
health
and well-being how we define illness how
we define aging
we can do that in pretty formal ways
that are useful so we can come back to
that
okay the goal qualia specifically was
it's the first product
that we brought to the market as a kind
of well-being enhancement
support and specifically well-being
enhancement
in the direction of increasing quality
of subjective experience and
certain aspects of performance
capability that are aligned with what
people
would traditionally think of associated
with cognitive enhancement but
take it a step up we think of what we
call sovereignty enhancement we define
sovereignty in a bigger way than i think
most people are used to thinking of it
we define sovereignty as the product
of three orthonormal vectors x y z
axis so one of them is intelligence one
is sentience one is
agency so intelligence is one's ability
to
process all kinds of information so
critical thinking and systemic thinking
and total body of knowledge and memory
focus information
uh speed of processing is all things
associated with intelligence
sentience is one's depth and subtlety
and robustness of uh feeling right of
sensing of experiencing so
empathy and mindfulness and awareness of
self and
other you know all those things live in
sentience
and then agency is one's
ability to maintain their integrity as
an individual and then act in the
universe and act
in the universe functionally so will
drive responsibility follow through all
those things so if you think of those
three as x y z axes and you think of
kind of whichever the shortest one is
defines volume of a sphere
we're trying to grow that sphere and uh
so when you
think of the fact that you know and you
know very well
someone's certain hormones being out of
balance certain neurotransmitters
certain cell energy dynamics being out
of balance can absolutely affect
people's will and drive can affect their
empathy their proprioception their
mindfulness can affect their
cognition you know various aspects of it
so
addressing the physiology of it is not
sufficient we also have to address the
psychology of it
and the you know what we kind of think
of as the human software side but the
human hardware side is necessary
and so we're saying what can we do to
support the underlying aspects of human
physiology that are involved in all of
those
to optimize uh and involve human
sovereignty so quality is the
first thing we brought to market to
support those
processes and you know it was several
years of r d where we were doing
personalized versions of that
in clinical settings i'm sure similar to
how you do
and then realizing that when we're
looking at
when we were looking at complex you know
blood chemistry genomes etc
there were some things that were very
different from one person to the next
and how to bring that kind of
personalized well-being science to
masses
is in our uh goal set but there were
many things that were common across
most people that were key to systems
optimization and
those were the early products were able
to start uh developing
well the thing that really impressed me
about this i mean you know we're
we do epigenetics and we do
nutrigenomics in our practice
and you know this is basically a bottle
full of uh
of nutrigenomic modifiers i had looked
into developing
a powder that included some of this
stuff
but what excited me was when i'm reading
through this i mean you
you you had taken what was the concept
in my mind and taken it to
just a whole new level with with what
you put in this stuff
and it was not only a combination of
product
but the actual dosages which you rarely
see in supplements at dosage levels that
are equivalent to what the research is
actually
showing i mean when i saw acetyl
l-carnitine at 800 milligrams algal dha
at 200 milligrams even bacopa monaria
which is one of my favorite supplements
at 300 milligrams ben fatia mean
mucuna to help boost dopamine in the
brain all of these things
were just really impressive for me
to to see that even adding the the
uridine
to the supplement in order to help with
the choline utilization
boost choline i mean you just don't see
that in supplements
and it was exciting to see this and when
i started recommending it to my clients
and i hadn't even taken it yet they were
reporting back to me how
outstanding they felt on this stuff
i have to say there's one thing though
that i would love to see in it
and it's holy basil which uh if i could
say there's one thing that would make
this thing
just perfect it would be holy basil
the process of how we developed it was
actually really fun i think you'll
appreciate so we started from a kind of
cognitive science point of view of
saying all right so what are all of
these subjective states
and capabilities cognitive and
you know other neurologically related
capabilities that
we're wanting to affect for people here
and that people are wanting when they go
to say
energy drinks or off-label smart drugs
or uh whatever and
so we we modeled that out it has to do
with short-term memory
and speed of memory and long-term memory
and verbal fluency
and digit span and arithmetic processing
and analytic thinking and synthetic
thinking and creativity and
focus and attention span you know all of
those cognitive metrics
and things like drive and emotional
resilience
with increased presence and subjective
flow state and so
it's very important to get that right
first because if you have just a subset
of it you're seeking to optimize a
subset of that it'll usually be at the
cost of some of the other important
metrics so
this is what's so commonly reported when
someone is using
a smart drug like adderall for off-label
purposes they'll increase
a part of their dopamine pathway without
the rest of the aspects of their
dopamine pathway or any of the other
neurotransmitter or other
you know kind of key neurologic pathways
such that they do have increased
say focus but maybe at the cost of other
important cognitive metrics like
aspects of memory and processing and
definitely at the cost of
you know say the ability for task
switching which can lead to
more aggravation irritability anxiety
and then of course you also have the
ability to i mean
if you use a exogenous override of an
endogenous regulatory system
then you're going to decrease the
regulatory capacity of that system i.e
dependence down regulation and addiction
and so our goal was how do we work
through the endogenous
pathways such that if someone used this
for some period of time and then stopped
rather than be down regulated and
addicted they would actually have their
baseline elevated
and so we're really supporting you know
endogenous regulatory capacity so we
started with modeling
all right here's all the things we're
wanting to affect subjectively
performatively
then we went through all the literature
of all the various sciences that we
could and said
what do we know across all the sciences
of which
aspects of physiology mediate and relate
to
those aspects of psychology and so
you know if we're talking about memory
there's asp you know
there's a lot that we know about
acetylcholine about glutamate about
catecholamines about specific receptor
sites about
specific kinds of synaptic processes so
we started modeling all of that out to
develop the whole interconnected set of
underlying physiology that we'd want to
be up regulating and then
the whole regulatory pathways associated
to say we're wanting to up regulate
these biosystems right and obviously
that's going to get all the way to
the whole system but in a weighted
fashion
and then we looked at what chemistries
mapped to being able to support those
systems and we got
a list of 500 or so chemicals that
we had a lot of data on and then we
started looking at which ones
are safe across the other systems you
know have good safety data which ones
have synergistic effects across multiple
systems
and then we paired it down to that
particular 42
ingredients and those specific doses
and the doses for some things seem high
compared to other supplements sometimes
they seem lower than someone would want
but it's
it's on purpose because say you're
looking at the macuna for the l-dopa
well we've got dlpa so you've got the
phenylalanine which will be converting
into tyrosine
and then acetyl tyrosine and then l-dopa
and then dopamine
so if you look at the fact that we've
got the phenylalanine and acetyl
tyrosine and
l-dopa and the you know p5p that's part
of the conversion process and some of
the other
minerals and vitamins are part of the
conversion process and then things that
are going to support
synaptic transporter proteins endogenous
mao b
inhibitors things that will sensitize d1
d2 receptors
you can't use the same dose of each of
those things that were effective in
isolation when you start having
synergies across the whole pathway so we
started really
looking at how do we have you know the
effective doses for optimizing
flow through pathways and then
interaction between pathways like
dopamine with the rest of catecholamines
with acetylcholine and glutamate with
the underlying cell energy processes and
and then deeper things like neurogenesis
and synaptogenesis
with regard to holy basil holy basil is
a beautiful herb obviously
adaptogenically especially for
ubiquitous adrenal stress you'll notice
that we have the phosphatidylserine
which has many of the similar effects in
terms of
hpa adaptogenic effects on
you know serotonin acth et cetera we
actually found
enough people that did not respond well
to holy basil that it didn't make it in
the were the kinds of people that were
looking for the effects primarily that
we'd have here
that it didn't make it in this final cut
but it was definitely used in many of
the versions and we will have products
coming out that will include it
yeah one of the the the aspect i like
about holy basil
is that the neuroplasticity and the bdnf
increases that you get with the holy
basil and that's that's
that's been my finding with it in
clinical practice as well
i mean it's anecdotal but
the cool thing about it is it raises it
causes increased expression of
fndc5 in the muscle which goes to the
liver and gets converted to irisin which
goes to the brain and boosts bdnf
which is the main purpose that we
typically focus in on
with the with the holy basil but i
love this this whole approach that you
have with
looking at enhancing existing systems
without
supplanting the system and i think
that's that's where
a lot of medicine has gone awry is that
in medicine
we focus and even in in wellness in
general
i mean we focus on trying to supplant
the body's a beautiful system the body
is an amazingly complex system that
for us to even have the concept that we
can micromanage it
is is just mind-blowing and
so even with with like all these
antioxidants that people take i mean
come on
we're we're producing uh what one times
10 to the 24th free radicals a day and
you think that taking vitamin c and
these high doses is going to make that
big of a difference in that system
is just ludicrous i mean you look at it
and you say well it's not that the
system's broken it's not the free
radicals are bad i mean we produce free
radicals for a good reason
so what we need to do is boost the
body's management capabilities of that
so boost the system that actually
handles it
give it that that little kick to say hey
i'm going to keep you in a healthy state
so that you can do this rather than me
trying to micromanage it and i love the
way you've done that with this product
yeah so there you know if you say how do
we can giving glutathione have benefit
for people totally does boosting
endogenous glutathione production have
more benefit
obviously then is there an excessive
need on glutathione
as a whole because of you know some
increased toxic exposure or something
that we could address or
or you know chronic subclinical
pathogens so we can do things to help
of course so it's it is a very deep and
nuanced thing i think the thing that i
like
you know i really love hearing you say
is the
the respect and reverence for the
intelligence of the body and nature and
universe rather than it's
it's a dumb system and so we have to fix
it you know
when you mention 10 to the 24th free
radicals per day and what is what do we
really think it means to manage that
when we think about a trillion metabolic
functions per second per cell give or
take
right and and the synchrony of all those
right
there is just radical parallel
processing happening every
cell having its own internal processing
dynamics that then are interacting and
not just every cell but every organelle
all the way down to you know the
fundamental physics of it
and so there is no way to top down
manage that
in fact we can mathematically prove it
right we can prove that it is a
that it is an np complete issue that is
non-computable
so then we say well how do we support
those endogenous regulatory systems and
that is a very different approach to
well-being science
you're listening to the iron man
executive with dr daniel stukler
be sure to check out the ironman
executive.com website for free offers
bonus materials and extended interviews
now back to the ironman executive show
well i want to shift gears a little bit
because i wanted to get to this during
this interview but
talking about most of my listeners are
major biohackers uh they're all about
you know trying different things uh the
n equals one
approach and i don't actually prefer
that term biohacking i
i prefer optimizing human potential in
in that regard
uh biohacking just seems almost in that
hedonic realm
but um you guys use the the term
neurohacking
and where do you see this this
neurohacking going i mean what's the
what's the future process of
neurohacking that you see
so just two quick little philosophic
things
you mentioned a couple times uh that the
goal of future medicine is not
purely hedonic or the future of
optimization
that old split between haydon and daemon
is actually one of the nonsense things
we have to dichotomies we have to
reconcile so when we talked about
optimizing human
experience and human capability
having a underlying philosophic model
that
shows that the way that people
contribute to the whole
is actually optimal for their own
quality of life experience
and as their quality of life goes up
it increases their capacity and
predisposition to contribute to the
whole
very much in the same way that a cell
relates to the whole body right the way
that
human relates to humanity and to
universe and so
we would not throw out hedonism we would
include and transcend it
right and i think when you said
eudemonia that's a good word for include
and transcend
that people's own experience their
experiential tone being optimized is
absolutely useful
for then optimizing their capability and
predisposition for serving meaningfully
and vice versa without deep meaningful
service their qualities of
personal subjective experience that just
don't happen and so i just
i just wanted to mention that real quick
the interview i did
just uh just two weeks ago with
steve cole who is a
psychoneuroimmunologist at ucla
he did a study on hedonism
versus eudemonic well-being and
it blew me away they went into the study
him and
barbara friedrichson went into the study
thinking you know they're going to see
similar outcomes of positive
physiological responses and they found
that the
on the psychological scales the hedonics
and the eudemonics scored
equally well on well-being scores but
then when they looked at the
health of the immune system they started
looking
deeper into these epigenetic marks and
and blood biomarkers and they found
this this is just amazing the hedonic
well-being group actually scored lower
than people that had
low well-being to begin with while the
eudemonic groups scored
off the chart and in the health of their
immune system
and yet they appeared the same on
psychological tests of well-being
what that means is that the decreased
immunity is going to lead to decreased
psychological scores over time
right right and so some of the team at
neural hacker wrote a really brilliant
paper on this i think it's going to
publish soon
but um if one is
pursuing states of experience that
through processes that create momentary
spikes but end up eroding baseline then
of course
you can have elevated state on the short
term and eroded baseline long term
if you are pursuing states of experience
where you actually want to evolve the
baseline
itself then it's a totally different
approach and this is the two marshmallow
experiment right we all
we all know this but it is very
meaningful to say it is actually
anti-addictive what it ends up creating
the highest quality of life which you
could say would be
smart hedonism if someone wants to
really have highest quality of
experience that gets higher over time
then it's not about short-term spikes
it's about the evolution of baseline
and the evolution of baseline means what
actually builds the integrity of the
system enduringly
i'm kind of confused on that one can you
explain that one just a little bit
more time somebody goes for the
chocolate cake they feel good in the
moment they feel shitty
over time as they eat a lot of chocolate
cake because
they got a dopamine spike but they got a
dopamine spike in a way that affected
the rest of their physiology
such that it's going to lead to an
imbalance in their dopamine opioid axis
and a bunch of other systems so then of
course as they feel shittier than they
crave more
dopamine spikes because their baseline
is lower
right their baseline well-being is lower
which then
wants to feel better more quickly and as
it wants to feel better quickly than
it's going to go for whether it was the
chocolate cake the cocaine or the
whatever it is that creates a hit
and so we can think of addiction as an
eroding base
you know some process to increase
subjective well-being quickly
that actually decreases the integrity of
the system that lowers the baseline
it creates more desperation to then feel
better which
leads to doing the same process you know
i got you
yeah so you're you were referring to the
the short-term aspects of it
and and how that responds yeah i agree
someone
even pursuing hedonism intelligently
which says i actually want to feel good
but i want to feel
continuously good and progressively more
so over a long period of time
a fundamentally different approach has
to be taken i still think that's going
to come down to though
you know like they they've found i mean
in psychological well-being scores the
people who pursued hedonism on a regular
basis they scored very well
on that psychological well-being just as
well as the ones that were
you know living life with a purpose per
se but
you know i i just i think that there is
there is some aspects that we're all
going to experience that hedonistic
approach but i think if we have that
overriding purpose
that vision of where where we want
things to be and
and we're living towards i mean just you
know one of the examples that dr cole
used was
you know the person who climbs mount
everest i mean sure you can look at that
as potentially a hedonistic
aspect but if they're doing it to show
humanity that that it can be done then
that's a whole different
psychological aspect to their well-being
that they're utilizing there okay the
dichotomy that i'm
speaking to that is worth reconciling is
there is an
old puritan distinction
where pleasure is a bad thing and
particular interpretation and so really
we're seeking
pleasure in the afterlife or something
right sacrifice is a good thing
and purpose and meaning end up not being
associated with pleasure
and that distinction is
an obsolete one right we can say that
the highest kinds of
the pleasure that are very real because
like you said you have some
psychological scores from people who are
pursuing
who are focused on their own state
versus focused on some larger things
that include their own state
and the key is focused on larger
purposes but that will end up
including their state rather than
excluding it and
so as people pursue being of you
use to larger than themselves that will
end up
inexorably leading to them feeling
better
and as to the degree that people
actually feel better they will have more
resources to show up more
so we would just like i would like to
have people think about
advancing their own subjective quality
of life
and advancing their utility to the whole
as being inner symbiotic with each other
i completely agree with that i think
that uh that kind of brings it all
together there and uh
and makes a lot of sense to me you know
my goal is to
get to the point where we can reverse
age and it's not a
and obviously it does have a hedonistic
component to it but in
in a sense it's more about an
over overriding uh for
me to be helping to create this new
paradigm and to
advance humanity in that regard because
i see it as possible
and people will look at it and say you
know it's hedonistic to want to
live forever well no not necessarily i
can see that
in that and what you just used as the
example there maybe we'll have
an opportunity a show to discuss
approaches to the future of
anti-aging sometimes that would be cool
that's that is my uh
my passion for sure so going down that
road a little bit and uh
and i know we're running a little short
on time but i want to ask you
what your vision is to take a look at 10
years down the road
where do you see medicine and you know
just life in general
i mean we're at this exponential growth
phase of technology and science
and 10 years is a is a millennium
what can we achieve in that amount of
time if we
think not just about individual
technologies but we think about
technological ecosystems that create
synergistic capacities across the
ecosystem i think it's that's a very
meaningful thing to think about for the
next 10 years
because we could just talk about robots
that do surgery better and
individual diagnostic technologies and
individual therapeutic technologies but
it's really the
that entire system's capability that's
interesting right
i think we will see some
radical progress in diagnostic and
assessment technologies
that'll be things like the evolution of
mass spec for metabolomics and maybe
home metabolomics so the quantified self
devices move from
relatively small number of metrics to a
lot of metrics and a lot of fidelity of
information that leads to big data
at the level of individuals i think
that'll be a huge
thing i think we'll probably even do
some further out stuff like laser
interferometry
for testing more blood metrics without
even pricking the blood we're already
doing
like you know nanobiosen technologies
for being able to do advanced pcr-like
technology from a single drop of blood
so i think ubiquitous data
bio data about people and then cognitive
and psychological data
will lead to our ability to do of course
assessment across lots of people but
also even big data
on a single individual because of
frequency of testing and all the things
that we get a test that will lead to
you know early disease indicators also
what we would call
you know need for support system
resilience indicators
but that tremendous amount of data will
have to be processed on
different kinds of processing platforms
so i think
combinatorial ai
interpretive platforms are going to be a
really key thing to be able to say all
right so we have
inflammatory metrics we have nutrient
metrics we have
you know proteomic transcriptomic
metabolomic etc all this data
how do we look at each of those
biometrics not just in relationship to a
reference range but in relationship to
all the other metrics
and see how those metrics are affecting
each other and how the causal cascades
happen
which things move first in response to
behaviors or environmental stimuli that
then lead to other things moving that
lead to recursive effects
and so and this is a this is a very
unique kind of
ai and it will actually require the
evolution of the
understanding of the of the ontology
of human physiology how the
regulatory systems interact so we take
kind of a complex adaptive systems and
cybernetic view of the human as a
as a complex regulatory system adaptive
system
and it allows us to then not just be
doing
machine learning on big data but
actually knowing what to look for for
complex causal
dynamics so that it actually drops that
nearly infinite amount of
information back into computable sets
and then i think therapeutic
technologies will be getting better
on the medicine side in terms of i mean
already seeing immuno oncology it's like
one of
it's one of the first things coming out
of
what we call traditional medicine
pharmaceutical medicine that is for
something that isn't acute that is
actually great right so really
happy to see that i think there will be
a lot in terms of therapeutic
technologies for
infection many different kinds mucosal
infection
humeral cellular infection for toxicity
and subclinical kind of detox
that's another key thing is the really
understanding subclinical pathology
and how to assess it and address it
and then of course how to prevent it
understanding more about
genetic expression and how to modulate
genetic expression
so there will be therapeutic dynamics at
each of those levels and
the key of what we'll be coming to is
moving towards personalized medicine not
just
at a personalized towards a few snips in
someone's genome or even common torques
of the genome but personalized to
all of that data that we have so we stop
thinking about ms as a disease or
rheumatoid arthritis as a disease
we start and we stop even thinking about
cognitive enhancement as a thing that is
optimized a certain way give them a
rassa tamar
we start thinking about all of the
different pathways that are involved
and the causal cascades the
multifactorial causal cascade so we see
someone's ms there might be thousands of
different
pathways that can contribute to the
deviation from homeostasis that leads to
ms and anyone's ms might be some
weighted subset and when i say ms i
could mean anxiety
alzheimer's anything right some weighted
subset of those factors that led to that
pathophysiology so then we
can know how to do differential
diagnosis across the whole underlying
causal set
possible causal set right the causal
phase base see what specific things are
actually going on
and then not be treating a disease
cluster but treating
the specific pathways that are going on
and again where sometimes we are
specifically reversing some aspect of
pathology
but we're primarily focused on
increasing
system resilience and homeostatic
capacity for the body to be able to do
that across
all kinds of dynamics and that you know
that looks like
increasing efficiency of cellular
function increasing efficiency of
mucosal membranes you know etc yeah i
agree with you and i
i would even take it a step further i
mean i in 10 years i mean with what
we've got going on right now with crispr
technology and you know i'm interviewing
a lot of the people in the field right
now
crispr the nanobots uh all of this stuff
i think within 10 years i mean
it absolutely is going to be a
bioinformatics
field no doubt about that but i i
really do see that we are going to be
stepping away from disease models
it's just not going to exist i mean
we're going to we're going to take care
of cancers we're going to take care of
heart disease before it even
comes about and if it does come about
it'll be something that they can go in
and do some editing on the
on the immune system and create a
response that is ideal
and we have a tool right now with crispr
that it's like given this it's like
being given a uh
teleporter and not have and not knowing
how it's used or or anything like that i
mean
we've got a technology that is ahead of
our knowledge
and i think once we start to learn how
to use this
i mean this technology i mean you can
order
crispr for your home basement to do it
do lab work in your basement i mean
that's how simple this technology is but
it's going to be
amazing what comes out of this and
nanotechnology
on top of that i mean i just uh i really
see a whole new realm
of of health uh and i think physicians
there's going to be
a little need for physicians most of the
time i mean you're going to be
looking at computer ai bioinformatics
systems you're going to be looking at
that can compute much greater amounts of
details than the human brain can
process as a clinician so you're going
to have
them running the show for these things
and
and i think it's going to be an exciting
time yeah so when we think about
exponential technology and medicine
so thing technology that enables more
technology of its kind on exponential
curves so we think of nanotechnology
synthetic biology crispr genome editing
ai et cetera one of the interesting
things is of course
you're getting so much more rate of
change right so much more change per
unit time and
continuously so that we can't have the
same adaptive time periods we've had in
the past and our intuitions from the
past
are less and less adequate at the same
at the same time
our chance of things up
increases exponentially too because
any increased power and we've seen this
with
all of the major environmental problems
that we see in the world or the
application of humans using technology
and even you know so many of them in the
biotech right that we're dealing with
health issues
technology has increased power
especially if it's not already
a self-organizing system has the ability
to have positive and
destructive applications and mostly
destructive not intentionally
but because we just didn't understand
the full causal dynamics that were
happening
and so with crispr for instance the
reductionist approach of this
single nucleotide polymorphism does this
thing so we're going to remove it
you know from the genome let's say we
take apoe4 but then we're starting to
get indication of the role of apoe4 and
parasitic
immune function and it doesn't
automatically lead to alzheimer's it
leads to increased predisposition if
environmentally triggered in some way so
i it's not that i'm not you know
fascinated by crispr we we
spend a lot of time with it but i think
that it is critical that we come to
understand
complex systems dynamics much much
better than we are even currently close
to
before we think we understand them well
enough to
edit the self-organizing code itself and
so in
as we are working towards that affecting
genetic expression through epigenetic
switches and through neutrogenomics
is awesome and genome editing requires
us increasing our level of understanding
tremendously
well and i think even when we get to the
point of the genome editing
you're still going to be having to deal
with this whole biospherical system
of the body interacting i mean you know
it's
the expression of 23 000 genes to make
over a million proteins
there's a lot going on between the code
itself and the outcome
and and i think that you know the
epigenetics is not going to be
going away we may get better at it but
it's still going to be a
major network of complex interactions
that just basically will come down to
you know
living the lifestyle that that promotes
the most optimal
function of the human being yeah one
more thing i'll say about the future of
medicine and well-being that we haven't
mentioned but that i think is really
critical and i'm sure you talk with your
audience about it often is
if we see before someone is
would normally be diagnosed with lupus
or some kind of rheumatism or whatever
we see certain
autoimmune antibodies expressing we see
certain cytokines expressing well we can
say okay so
this inflammatory marker causes this
illness or we see
certain hormones out of balance before
another illness
obviously what that means is that that
inflammatory marker
that hormone was part of a causal
cascade but it was not the beginning of
the causal cascade
right those are messenger molecules
there's something upstream from that
we can go all the way upstream and say
what would the tier one
deviation from the homeostatic integrity
of the system b
that leads to that process and you say
all right well
health is defined as the homeostatic
capacity not being in homeostasis
but the total homeostatic capacity of
the system and more robust health means
more homeostatic resiliency
ability to handle larger stressors
larger deviations from homeostasis
without actually leaving
homeostatic ranges cool so that's health
then we say aging is different than
disease
disease is some deviation from
homeostasis
that exceeded the system's capacity to
stay within
functional ranges leading to
pathophysiology
aging is decreased homeostatic
resilience of the system so the system
might still be in homeostasis across any
particular metric but it has less
resilience so increase susceptibility to
disease so that distinction ends up
being
meaningful but you come all the way up
and you say well it initially starts
with some
deviation from homeostasis that exceeded
the system's capacity
illness specifically i mean the system's
capacity to respond to so that initial
deviation is always
going to be either the way the system is
interacting the way
the human here but we could say this for
any biological system the way the system
is interacting with its environment
that is not aligned with what its
evolutionary code can process
or the overarching behavior of the
system that's not aligned with its
evolutionary code or an actual problem
the evolutionary code problem of
evolutionary code
means genetic predisposition for illness
independent of environmental expression
but let's just throw that category off
to the side for a minute and take the
other two so
interface with the environment means
taking in too much of something it
shouldn't have which we call toxicity of
various kinds
pathogenicity etc not taking in enough
of something deficiency
overarching behavior of the system means
exercise posture sleep you know
lifestyles
stress lifestyle things where the system
is behaving in ways that again are not
what it's evolutionary code adapted to
be able to do well
which leads to some kind of system
stress dynamics
so we come up to those those tier one
causes and we say all right well we want
to be able to
optimize human wellness we actually want
to make sure we're addressing things at
that level right the homeostatic
resilience the whole system and also
decreasing the tier 1 dynamics since so
many of those
are the interface with the environment
where we have ubiquitous
toxicity exposures whether we're talking
about
chlorine in the water to deficiency from
not enough minerals in the water to not
enough minerals or humic and fulvic
acids or microbiome in the soil where
the food is coming from
to vocs in the paint inside we have
modified our environment post-industrial
revolution
in a way that is not what our genetic
code adapted to
process that is a tier one cause of so
much illness so
in an environment that has a lot more
nitric oxide in the air and more
particulate
emissions and higher co2 and you know
etc
and ubiquitous glyphosate and can
people be optimally healthy in that
environment well
no they can do things to support
themselves to be healthier than they
would be otherwise but this is where our
health
and the health of the environment that
we're in an osmotic gradient
relationship with
is interlinked and this is where
optimizing human health and optimizing
the health of the entire
entire biosphere and the and the way we
design our built world
the toxicology of it etc are all key so
this is where we'd say i can't we can't
actually talk about the future of
medicine
or the future of wellness well-being
independent of the topic of
the comprehensive redesign of the way we
do
being human on this planet and all of
the aspects that are inter-affecting
i agree that is very well said the
the one area that uh we may differ in
and i'm not sure
what your thought process is on this but
i kind of lean towards the
the programmed aspect of aging in our
genome it's a
we're a small group of of
of philosophical belief systems that
that our dna is actually in a sense
programmed to to start to down regulate
a lot of the systems that we have
and i think that that's
that's going to be a major area of the
genome editing once we start to identify
these
these programs that we carry that tell
the system you know what
don't function as well at this don't
don't do
as well in monitoring as you have i mean
we've got examples in nature of
animals that show no signs of senescence
whatsoever so
i think it's a combination of the two i
think there is there's absolutely this
environmental and biospherical
aspect of the things that we interact
with that are going to contribute to
to this process but i think that there's
also a very strong component of
uh genetically programmed deterioration
of the human being
this is probably true if we could have
dynamics that were more like lobster or
jellyfish
in this way that is obviously very
meaningful and i think
you know sens and rad and those
organizations are definitely doing deep
dives in
what what that could be i think
even before we identify that there's a
lot we can do
to deal with the likely effects of it
which is can we induce
increased autophagy of senescent cells
can we protect cells from senescence can
we increase
development of more stem cells and their
differentiation throughout tissues yes
you know so we can do those
then of course if we can deal with the
underlying
mechanisms that lead to more senescence
than is necessary in the first place
obviously that's powerful well i don't
want to keep you all night and i could
certainly do that
this has been a fascinating conversation
and uh
and really thought provoking as well and
i'd love to have you back on the show
to discuss some some other aspects that
i would love to get into i had a whole
list of
additional questions that i didn't even
come close to so
well i love being on the show i love
your approach to
health and wellness and you know
vitality and eudaimonia optimization
and what you're sharing with people and
you know why we call it neurohydra
collective
is because the goals that we seek to
you know help bring about here obviously
can only happen
in a meaningful meaningful partnerships
and symbiosis with everyone that's
working towards similar goals
so i look forward to exploring how we
can continue to
be aligned and mutually supportive as
much as possible in these shared goals
awesome well i certainly appreciate your
time and uh
look forward to further conversations
likewise thank you my friend
[Music]
well as you can tell i could have
probably gone all day in my
conversations with daniel schmokenberger
he
is a fascinating individual and we've
had some conversations
unrecorded over the past couple of weeks
and we have a couple more planned but he
just really helps me to take my brain to
areas
that um i don't expect not only from his
qualia product but also from his
conversations
themselves he is an individual that is
going to change the world
and he fits very well into our vision of
the appearance center for human
potential as far
as shifting the whole paradigm of a
process
in our situation it's of the health and
wellness process
in his i can't even put it into a box
he's talking about
economies he's talking about health and
wellness he's
talking about commerce i mean everything
he talks about
philosophically is about this systems
approach so
very fascinating be sure to check out
the links
in the podcast details where we will
have links to
the neuro hacker product be sure to use
the
code limitless and you can get a 10 off
when you order the product with the
discount code
it's not an inexpensive product but i
can tell you the quality of what you get
and the ingredients that went in there
you cannot
break it down and buy those individual
ingredients at those dosages
for a lesser price so it's a good
product it's
a excellent mix of nootropics
that are designed to enhance the system
not to supplant the system
so be sure to check it out and also be
sure to check out the appearon dot
academy to see about all of the coaching
classes that we talked about at the
beginning
and i look forward to speaking with you
guys next week
until then everyone be epic
thank you for tuning in to the iron man
executive join us each week as dr
stikler explores the world of human
potential
optimization and unlocks the limitless
boundaries of human physiology
be sure to check out the ironman
executive.com website for bonus material
and news of upcoming events
until next week may your potential be
limitless and your life epic